<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great case of tythes truly stated, clearly opened, and fully resolved. By a countrey-man, A.P.</title>
            <author>Pearson, Anthony, 1628-1670?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E931_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866694</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866694</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E931[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great case of tythes truly stated, clearly opened, and fully resolved. By a countrey-man, A.P.</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Anthony, 1628-1670?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread-Eagle neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLVII. [1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A.P. = Anthony Pearson. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decem. 6"; "P [illegible]".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118978:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT CASE OF TYTHES Truly ſtated, clearly opened, and fully reſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Countrey-man,</hi> A. P.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls. MDCLVII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118978:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118978:2"/>
            <head>To the Countrey-men, Farmers, and Husbandmen of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is for your ſakes that this ſmall Treatiſe is ſent abroad, that in a matter wherein you are ſo much concern'd, you might be truly informed: And becauſe there are many differing opinions, and of late yeers have been great diſputes concerning the right of Tythes, which makes the caſe ſeem difficult to be reſolved, I have given you the ſubſtance of all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I could finde written, or hear diſcourſed touching that point; and for more then two yeers laſt paſt I have made much enquiry into it; and if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who have ſomething to ſay for them, which is not herein touched, or in ſome generall head compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, it ſhall be acceptable to me to receive it.</p>
            <div type="method">
               <head>The Method of the Diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>Firſt, I have begun with tything amongſt the Jewes, which either in precept or example, is the foundation for all others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118978:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Secondly, I have given you a ſhort view of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Opinions, Decrees and Practiſes of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church concerning them, and from thence-downward untill this day, which is enough to clear the whole point.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Out of which having made ſome ſhort Obſervations, I ſtate the caſe, as it concerns us in England.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, And then hearing what every one hath to ſay for them, and giving them particular An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers,</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>I</hi> proceed to ſatisfie ſome great Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo conclude the whole in as much brevity, as the variety of the ſubject would permit.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. P.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118978:3"/>
            <head>OF TYTHING Amongſt the IEWES.</head>
            <p>GOD having choſen <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons for the Office of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and the reſt of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> for the ſervice of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, he gave unto the <hi>Levites</hi> all the tenth in <hi>Iſrael</hi> for an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for their ſervice, and they were to have no inheritance among the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Levites</hi> out of their Tythe were to offer up an Heave-offering of it for the Lord, even the tenth part of the tythe, and give it unto <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt for himſelf and his ſons; and no other portion had the Prieſts out of the tythes, but they were for the Levites that did the common ſervices of the Tabernacle, for the ſtrangers, for the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and the widowes.</p>
            <p>Beſides the tenth of the tythe, the Prieſts had the firſt ripe fruits of the ground, of Wheat, of Barley, of Figs, of Grapes, of Olives, of Pomgranates and Dates, at what quantity the owner pleaſed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45.13</note> a Heave-offering alſo of corn, wine, oyl, fleece and the like were given to the Prieſts at the 60. part, ſometimes at the 50. or more, at the devotion of the owner.</p>
            <p>Of Cattel alſo the firſt-born were the Lords, paid to the Prieſts, of clean beaſts in kinde, of unclean in money, with a fifth part added: Alſo divers parts of the ſacrifices were appointed for the Prieſts.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But no tythes did the Prieſts receive of the people; for thoſe belonged to the <hi>Levites</hi> that were appointed over the tabernacle, and the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof to bear it, to take it down and ſet it up, to ſerve <hi>Aaron</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118978:4"/>and his ſons, and to do the Services of the tabernacle, and keep the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments thereof, and their ſervice chiefly was upon removing of the Hoſt; for better ordering whereof, and every ones ſervice, they were divided into three parts, the <hi>Koathites,</hi> the <hi>Gerthonites</hi> and the <hi>Mararites,</hi> and theſe received tythes of the people, and out of them a tenth part they delivered to the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, when <hi>Solomon</hi> had builded a temple, and placed the Ark therein, other offices were appointed for the <hi>Levites;</hi> one part of them were to be ſingers, another to be porters, and take the charge of the gates of the Temple; another to be keepers of the treaſury: others of them alſo were placed abroad in the country,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.</note> on the Weſt ſide of <hi>Iordan</hi> 1700. and on the Eaſt ſide 2700.</p>
            <p>By this time alſo the poſterity of <hi>Aaron</hi> being much increaſed, the Prieſts were divided into 24 ranks or courſes, according to the names of their Families, and every ones attendance was required by turns; and hereupon <hi>Zacharias</hi> is ſaid to be of the courſe of <hi>Abiah,</hi> and to execute the Prieſts office, and burn incenſe as his turn came, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. and the firſt of the firſt rank had the pre-eminence and was the High Prieſt, and ſo every one according to their precedency were preferred.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Levites</hi> that were ſingers were divided as the Prieſts into 24. ranks or courſes; the porters into five parts, one part to every of the four gates of the temple, and the five to <hi>Aſuppim,</hi> i.e. the <hi>Councell-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The treaſury was generally committed to one, as the chief; but under him to two ſorts of other officers; one to keep the treaſures of the Houſe of the Lord, and thoſe things that were offered to the Lord; and the other to keep the dedicate things: In theſe treaſuries were put the ſecond tythes, the offerings of all ſorts of people, which were for the uſes and ſervices of the temple, for the fatherleſs, the ſtranger and the widow.</p>
            <p>After the captivity and new dedication of the temple, it appears that in many particulars their Laws, Ordinances and Cuſtoms were very much changed, eſpecially in this of tything: But not being much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to this diſcourſe, I ſhall paſs them over; onely from theſe ſhort hints let the Reader underſtand, that though the Prieſts and Levites were both of the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> yet was the prieſthood ſetled in the ſons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the offices of the prieſts were quite different from the Levites, and ſo was their maintenance diſtinct, as before is herein plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed.</p>
            <p>Theſe Prieſts and Levites being ſeparated for the work of the Lord, in the tabernacle and in the temple they miniſtred according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the firſt Covenant, which were figures for the time then preſent, and ſhadows of good things to come.</p>
            <div type="history">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118978:4"/>
               <head>A view of the Doctrines, Decrees and Practiſes of TYTHING, from the Infancy of the Chriſtian Church untill this day.</head>
               <p>BVt in the fulneſs of time God raiſed up another Prieſt, Chriſt Jeſus, who was not of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> nor conſecrated after the order of <hi>Aaron;</hi> for he pertained to another tribe, of which no man gave at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance at the Altar, who (having obtained a more excellent Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a greater and more perfect Tabernacle, not of the former build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being the ſum and ſubſtance of all the patterns of things under the firſt Covenant) put an end to the firſt prieſthood, with all its ſhadowes, ſigures and carnall ordinances, and changing the prieſthood which had a command to take <hi>tythes</hi> of their brethren, there was made of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alſo a change of the Law, and a diſannulling of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment going before, which was but impoſed untill the time of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>And the Apoſtles and Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> when he had finiſhed his Office upon earth, by offering up himſelf through the eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a ſacrifice without ſpot unto God, did not look back to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the former <hi>Priesthood,</hi> but teſtified an end was put unto them, and witneſſed againſt the temple wherein the prieſts miniſtred, for which <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned to death, againſt circumciſion, ſaying, <hi>It was not that of the flesh;</hi> againſt the Paſſeover, prieſts, &amp;c. and preached up Chriſt Jeſus and his Doctrine, the new and living way, which was not made manifeſt while as the firſt tabernacle was ſtanding: Nor did they go about to eſtabliſh the Law by which <hi>tythes</hi> were given in the former <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> but freely they preached the Goſpel which they had received, and did not require any ſetled maintenance, but lived of the free offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and contributions of the Saints, who by their Miniſtry were turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At Jeruſalem and thereabouts, ſuch was the unity of heart amongſt the Saints in the Apoſtles time, that all things were in common,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 4.3, 4.</note> and none wanted; and as many as were poſſeſſors of Lands or Houſes ſold them, and brought the price and laid it down at the Apoſtles feet, and it was diſtributed unto every man according as he haſt need.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Church</hi> gathered by <hi>Mark</hi> at <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame rule as the Saints did at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. in vita Marc.</note> having all things in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: And <hi>Philo Iudeus</hi> a famous Author of that time reporteth, that not onely there, but in many other provinces, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> lived toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſocieties.</p>
               <p>In the Churches at <hi>Antioch,</hi> the Saints poſſeſſed every man his own eſtate; ſo likewiſe in <hi>Galatia</hi> and <hi>Corinth,</hi> where the Apoſtle ordained that weekly offerings for the Saints ſhould be made by every one as God had bleſſed him;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 11.29.</note> and by theſe offerings (which were put into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118978:5"/>the hands of the Deacons of the Churches) were all the ſervices and needs of the Church ſupplied.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>By example of theſe the courſe of monethly offerings ſucceeded in the next Ages,<note place="margin">Vide Synod. Gangr. Can. <hi>60.</hi>
                  </note> not exacted, but freely given at the bounty of every man, as appears plainly by <hi>Tertullian in Apologet. ch.</hi> 39. where upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Gentiles with the pietie and devotion of Chriſtians, he ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever we have in the treaſury of our Churches, is not raiſed by taxation, as though we put men to ranſome their Religion, but every man once a moneth, or when it pleaſeth himſelf, beſtoweth what he thinks good, and not without he liſteth; for no man is compelled, but left free to his own diſcretion: and that which is given is not bestowed in vanity, but in relieving the poor, and upon children deſtitute of parents, and maintenance of aged and feeble perſons, men wracked by Sea, and ſuch as are condemned to the Mettal-mines, banished into Iſlands, or caſt into priſon, profeſsing the true God and the Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this way of contribution continued in the Church till the great perſecution under <hi>Maximinian</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> about the yeer 304. as <hi>Euſebius</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ch. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> which alſo appears by the writings of <hi>Tertullian, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen, Cyprian</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>About this time alſo ſome lands began to be given to the Church, and the revenue of them were brought into the treaſury of the Church, and belonged to the Church in common, and was diſtributed as other offerings, by the Deacons and Elders; but the Biſhops or Miniſters medled not therewith: for <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is not lawful for any Miniſter of the Church to poſſeſs lands (given to the Church) to his own uſe;</hi> And cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Miniſters, <hi>Let us depart from the Prieſts of PHAROAH, who injoy earthly poſſeſsions, to the Prieſts of the Lord who have no portion in the earth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>16</hi> Homily upon Geneſis, fol. <hi>26.</hi> ch. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> And in another place he ſaith, <hi>It behoveth us to be faithfull in diſpoſing the rents of the Church, that we our ſelves devour not thoſe things which belong to the widows and the poor, and let us be content with ſimple dyet and neceſſary apparel.</hi> And <hi>Vrban</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome Anno</hi> 227. did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That the Church might receive Lands and Poſſeſsions offred by the faithfull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vrban <hi>1.</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. c. <hi>12.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> e. <hi>161.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but not to any particular mans benefit, but that the Revenues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of should be diſtributed as other offerings, as need required.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian Epiſt.</hi> 27.34.36.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> about the year 250. alſo teſtifieth the ſame, and ſheweth that the Church maintained many poore, and that her own Dyet was ſparing and plain, and all her expences full of fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proſper</hi> alſo ſaith,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>21.</hi> de vita contemplativa.</note> That a Miniſter able to live of himſelf, ought not to participate of the goods of the Church; for ſaith he, <hi>They that have of their own, and yet deſire to have ſomewhat given them, do not receive it without great ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Council at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Con. Ant. cap. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 340. (finding that much fault had been amongſt the Deacons to whom it properly belonged) did ordain
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118978:5"/>hat the Biſhops might diſtribute the Goods of the Church, but required that they took not any part to themſelves, or to the uſe of the Prieſts and brethren that lived with them, unleſſe that neceſſity did juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, uſing the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Having Food and Rayment, be therewith content.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe times,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>11.</hi> in Acta. Tom. <hi>6.</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Savili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana, pag. <hi>897.</hi>
                  </note> in many places the Chriſtian Converts joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Societies and choſe a ſeparated life, ſelling what they had, and living together in common after the example of the former Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Jeruſalem, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> notes, who lived about the yeer 400. by whoſe writings it alſo appears, that there was not the leaſt uſe or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the payment of tythes in theſe former Ages.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Church</hi> now living altogether by free offerings of Lands, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and goods, the people were much preſſed to bountiful Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for holy uſes, as may be ſeen by the Writings of <hi>Hierome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Homil. <hi>43.</hi> ad Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> who brought the Jewiſh liberality in their payments of tenths, for an example, beneath which they would not have Chriſtians determine their charity, where <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes, he ſpeaks theſe things not as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding or forbidding that they ſhould give more, yet as thinking it ſit that they ſhould not give leſſe then the tenth part. <hi>Hierome</hi> alſo doth earneſtly admoniſh them to give bountifully to the poore,<note place="margin">Ad cap. <hi>3</hi> Malachia.</note> and double honor to him that labors in the Lords work; not binding at all to offer this or that part, leaving them to their own liberty, but preſſing they might not be more ſhort then the Jews were.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Milan</hi> about the year 400. preached up tenths to be offered up for holy uſes,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>5.</hi> Serm. fer. <hi>2.</hi> poſt dom. <hi>1.</hi> quadrageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma; &amp; vide Serm. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſ. Danivi.</note> (as the phraſe then was) as may be ſeen in his Sermon of Repentance, but his Authority he produceth wholly from <hi>Moſes</hi> writings, and quotes divers ſentences, and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the people that if they would not pay their renths, God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to a <hi>tenth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo</hi> hath a whole Homily for the right of eythes,<note place="margin">In Serm. de temp. in Tom. <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Hoec eſt <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> Domini juſtiſsimae conſuetudo, ut ſi tu illi dicimam non dederis, tu ad decimam revoceris. <hi>And afterwards with much earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Decimae ex debit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> requiruntur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as dare noluerit, res alienas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſit; &amp; quanti pauperes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocis uba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſe habitat, illo decimas non dante, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me mortui fueriut, tantoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homicidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reus ante Tribunal aeterni judici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> apparebit, quia à Domiuo pauperibus delegati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſuis uſibus reſervavit. Qui er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſibi aut praemiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comparare, aut pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caterum deſiderat indulgentiam prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reri, reddat decimam.</note> who calls upon thoſe that have no fruits of the earth, to pay the tenth of whatſoever they live by; and ſaith, the neglect of payment of tythes is the cauſe of ſterility and blaſting; &amp; agrees with <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his threats, That God would reduce them to a tenth; &amp; tells them, that not paying their tythes they ſhall be found guilty at Gods Tribunal, of the death of all the poor that periſh through want in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they dwell; and bids them that would either get reward, or deſire the pardon of their ſins, to pay their tythes. Theſe two great Biſhops agree, and from the Law given to the Iſraclites, take their whole Doctrine, and their own opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on impoſe with ſo heavy penalties: But yet take notice to what end they required them, That the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118978:6"/>poor might not want, and ſaith that God hath reſerved them for their uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo,</hi> (called the great) who was Pope from 440. to 460. was likewiſe very earneſt and large in ſtirring up every mans devotion to offer to the Church part of his received fruits, but ſpeaks not a word of any certain quantity, as may appeare by his Sermons <hi>De jejunio decimi miuſis &amp; Eleemoſynis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Severin</hi> alſo, about the year 470. ſtirred up the Chriſtians in <hi>Panonia,</hi> who in example of his bounty, gave the tenth of their fruits to the poor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> not onely admoniſheth the payment of tythes from <hi>Moſes</hi> Law,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>16.</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. &amp; diſt. <hi>5.</hi> de conſecrat. c. <hi>16</hi> Vt in lege jube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur Domino de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rerum dare</note> but alſo the obſerving the time of <hi>Lent,</hi> conſiſting of ſix Weeks, out of which take the Sundayes, and there remains thirty ſix dayes, the tenth part of the year, fractions of dayes omitted; this tenth of time he would have given to God, ſaying, <hi>We are commanded in the Law to give the tenth of all things unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And from the Opinions of theſe and other ancient Fathers, who took their ground from the Law, Tythes, Eaſter, Pentecoſt, and other things, came to be introduced and brought into the Church.<note place="margin">As is teſtified by <hi>Agobard</hi> Bish. of <hi>Lyons,</hi> a highly eſteemd man, in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe De diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatione, &amp;c. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Sacrilegos, pag. <hi>276.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding the Doctrine and hard threats of ſome of the great Biſhops of that time, it was not a generally received Doctrine that tythes ought to be paid, nor till about the year 800. was any thing by the then Church determined or ordained touching the quantity that ſhould be given, though (no doubt) in many places amongſt the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the devouter ſort, tenths, or greater parts of their annual encreaſe were given, according to the Doctrine of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>The offerings of the Church in theſe Ages were received and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of in maintainance of the Prieſts, and relief of thoſe that were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed;<note place="margin">Be not offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the word Prieſt; no other can be given to this age; for the title as then 'twas given to them, ſo it was owned by them.</note> neither had the Prieſts ſuch a particular intereſt in the profits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, as of late time they have uſurped; all that was received where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in the Biſhoprick, was as a common Treaſury, and was diſpenſed one fourth part to the Prieſts, out of which every one had his portion; another fourth part to the relief of the poor, ſick, and ſtrangers; a third to the building and repairing of places for publique meetings, called Churches &amp; the fourth to the Biſhop. And generally, then the Biſhop lived in ſome Monaſtery, and his Clergy with him, from whence he ſent them out to preach within the Countryes in his Dioceſſe, and there they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſuch offerings as were made, and brought them to the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.<note place="margin">I call it Church becauſe it was then ſo eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I muſt uſe ſuch words as may give the Reader a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what I ſay.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And though divers of the Fathers, Popes and Biſhops, did declare that tythes were due, and ought to be paid, none of the firſt eight gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councils of the Church did ever ſo much as mention the Name of Tythes, or declare them a duty. The nineth held at <hi>Lateran,</hi> under P. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixtus</hi> the ſecond, about the year 1119. mentions tythes, but ſpeaks onely of thoſe which had been given to the Church by ſpecial conſecration; ſo doth alſo the Council held under <hi>P. Alexander</hi> the third, <hi>An.</hi> 1180.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118978:6"/>but that onely inhibits appropriations to religious Houſes, without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a Biſhop; for at that time people being led to believe that their tythes ought to be given for the uſe of the poor, did chiefly diſpoſe them to the Heads and Governors of religious Houſes, who kept open Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality for the poor, and entertainment of ſtrangers, and were eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed holy, as good Treaſurers for the needy, who took care of diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, as is teſtified by <hi>Caſsian</hi> the Hermit. But that Council ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much given to the poor, little to the Prieſts, made that Decree to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the peoples freedom; and indeed, by this time much wickedneſſe was crept into theſe Houſes, as Hiſtories relate.</p>
               <p>Nor was any Law, Canon, or Conſtitution of any general Council as yet found, that purpoſely commanded the payment of tythes, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that expreſly ſuppoſed them a duty of common right, before the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> held in the year 1215. under P. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, about which time the Popes Authority was grown powerful, and the Canons more received into practice that before were little, eſpecially herein obeyed.</p>
               <p>About the yeers 800, 900, 1000. and after, Tythes were called the Lords goods,<note place="margin">Res dominicae, dominica ſubſtantia, Dei cenſus, Patrimonia pauperum, tributa egentium animarum, ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia pauperum, hoſpitum peregrinorum.</note> the patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the poor, &amp;c. Whence alſo the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Nants</hi> declared the Clergie was not to uſe them as their own, but as commended to their truſt; and they were not then given for the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, but to be diſpoſed of for the uſes of the poor.<note place="margin">Non quaſi ſuis, ſed quaſi commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, non ab hominibus, ſed ab ipſo Deo ſunt inſtitutae.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And at this time no regard was had to the nature of the increaſe; but whatſoever did ariſe in profit, whether by trade, merchandize, or husbandry, the tenth was required to be paid for tythes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He preaching on <hi>Zacheus</hi> charity, ſayes, Dedit proprium, &amp; reddi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic alienum. Graviter ergo peccant qui decimas &amp; primitias non reddunt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus, ſed eas pro voluntate diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buunt indigentibus.</note>But ſtill the people had more minde to give them for the poor rather then the prieſts, as may be underſtood by the complaint of <hi>Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the third, who cryed out againſt thoſe that gave their tythes and firſt fruits to the poor, and not to the prieſts, as haynous offenders; his own words take in the margin.</p>
               <p>Alſo a generall Council held at <hi>Lyons</hi> under <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> the tenth in the yeer 1274.<note place="margin">Vt nulli hominum deinceps liceat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimas ſuas ad libitum ut amea ubi vellet aſsignare, ſet Matrici Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae omnes decimas perſolverent.</note> it was conſtituted, that it ſhould not thenceforth be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for men to give their tythes of their own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure where they would, as it had been before, but pay all their tythes to the Mother Church. By theſe it may be ſeen, that though the people, who then generally were Papiſts, did believe they ought to pay them,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118978:7"/>yet were they free to diſpoſe them where they pleaſed, till theſe Popiſh Councils reſtrained their librrty.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Non ſunt ferendi qui vaerijs artibus decimas Eccleſiis obvenientes ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here moliuntur, ant qui ab aliis ſolven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das temere occupant, &amp; in rem ſuam vertunt, cum decimarum ſolutio debita ſit Deo, &amp; qui eas dare noluerins, aut dantes impediunt, res alienas inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt: Praecipit igitur ſancta Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, omnibus cujuſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gradus &amp; conditionis ſint, ad qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s decimarum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutio ſpecta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ut ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (ad quas dejure te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentur) in poſterum Cathedrali aut quibuſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliis Eccleſiis vel perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quibus legitime debentur, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greperſolvant: Qui vero cas aut ſubſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hunt, aut impediunt, Exoommunicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur: Nec ab hoc crimine, niſi plona reſtitutione ſecuta abſolvantur.</note>But the great Decree which ſpeaks moſt plain, and till which nothing was given foath which did-directly conſtitute them, but rather ſtill ſuppoſed them as due by ſome former right, was made at the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> under Pope Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us the fourth, about the year 1560. And yet that great Council followed the Doctrine of their Father, and ſaid they were due to God, and had no new Authority for their great Decree which they command to be obeyed under the penalty of excommunication.</p>
               <p>Having thus briefly run over the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal State abroad, from the Infant-purity of the Church, to the height of the Papal Dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and given a ſmall glimpſe through every Age to the point in hand, I ſhall now more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly return to what may concern this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not trouble the Reader with a relation of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> and his eleven Diſciples coming into <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſent by <hi>Philip</hi> the A poſtle in the reign of <hi>Arviragus,</hi> as Hiſtories re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; nor of the converſion of King <hi>Lucius</hi> afterwards, who is ſaid to give great endowments to the Church: Nor of the <hi>British</hi> Chriſtians, nothing at all appearing of the payment of tythes in their dayes: But paſſing by them, and thoſe many years wherein the barbarous <hi>Saxons</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ran this Nation, exerciſing moſt cruel perſecutions, till the very name of Chriſtian was blotted out, and thoſe Heathens ſeated in the quiet poſſeſſion of a ſevenfold Kingdom in this Land.</p>
               <p>About the year 600. or ſoon after, <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt new Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſent over <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monk into <hi>England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> by whom <hi>Ethelbert</hi> King of <hi>Kent</hi> was converted, and by him and his followers in proceſſe of time, other parts of the Nation, and others of the Kings were alſo brought to their faith. This <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was a Canon Regular, and both he and his Clergy for long time after followed the example of former Ages, living in common upon the offerings of their Converts; &amp; thoſe that received them were joined in ſocieties in imitation of the primitive practice, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch direction ſent him by Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> that in the tenderneſſe of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Church he &amp; his Clergy ſhould ſtill imitate the community of all things uſed in the prituitive times, under the Apoſtles, that they might not make their Religion burthenſom.</p>
               <p>But afterwards, having brought a great part of the Nation to their faith, they began to preach up the old <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine, That tythes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118978:7"/>ought to be paid; and having taught the people that the pardon of ſin might be merited by good works, and the torments of Hell be avoided by their charitable deeds, it was no hard matter when that was believed, to perſwade them not onely to give their tythes, but alſo their Lands, as the outward Riches of thoſe called Religious Houſes then, here and elſewhere may teſtifie; for in this Nation they and the Clergy had almoſt gotten the third part of the whole Land; and ſo beſotted were the poor ignorant people, that had not a Law againſt <hi>Mortmain</hi> prevented it, a far greater part of the Nation had been in their hands.</p>
               <p>As conceruing Laws and Canons for tythes amongſt the <hi>Saxons,</hi> it is reported, That in the year 786. two Legates were ſent from Pope <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> the firſt, to <hi>Offa</hi> K. of <hi>Mercland,</hi> and <hi>Aelfwolfe</hi> K. of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who made a Decree that the people of thoſe two Kingdoms ſhould pay tythes.</p>
               <p>Alſo that <hi>Aethelulph</hi> K. of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> in the year 855. made a Law, That the tythe of all his own Lands ſhould be given to God and his ſervants, and ſhould be enjoyed free from all taxes: Great difference is amongſt Hiſtorians about this Grant, few agreeing in the words or ſubſtance of it, as <hi>Selden</hi> ſhews, ſome reſtraining it to the tythe of his own Demeſne Lands; others to the tenth part of his Land; others to the tythe of the whole Nation. At that time the Nation being under groat and heavy preſſures by <hi>Danish</hi> irruptions, inteſtive wars,<note place="margin">Promeae reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio animae &amp; Regni &amp; popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li.</note> great ſpoiles and miſeries, he called a Council, where were preſent <hi>Bernredus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> K. of <hi>Mercia,</hi> and <hi>Edmund</hi> K. of <hi>Eaſt-Angles,</hi> and they to remove the heavy judgements then over them, grants the tythe of all their Land to God and his ſervants.</p>
               <p>K. <hi>Athelſtone,</hi> about the year 930. K. <hi>Edmund,</hi> about the year 940. K. <hi>Edgar,</hi> about the year 970. K. <hi>Ethelred</hi> about the year 1010. K. <hi>Knute</hi> about the yeare 1020. <hi>Edward the Conſeſſor,</hi> and others of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, made ſeveral Laws for tythes, as Hiſtories report.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quoniam Divina Miſrecordia pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidente cognovimus eſſe diſpoſitum, &amp; longe lati<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praedicante Eccleſia, ſonac omnium auribus divulgatum. Quod, Eleemoſynarum largitione poſſunt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvi vincula peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; adquiri Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtium praemia gaudioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Ego <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> Dei gratia <hi>Anglorum</hi> Rex, parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habere voleus cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illis qui felici commer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio Caelestia pro terrenis Commutant, Dei amore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punctus, &amp; pro ſalute, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae meae, &amp; patris mei Matriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> meae, &amp; omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meorum, &amp; anteceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>&amp;c. And ſo he goes on, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firms divers things that divers had gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the Ch. as tythes, &amp; other things.</hi>
                  </note>The <hi>Normans</hi> afterwards entring this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſubduing it to themſelves, <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> confirmed the Liberties of the Church; ſo did <hi>H.</hi> the firſt, <hi>H.</hi> 2. K. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and it may be others of the ſucceeding Kings did the like.</p>
               <p>Some Epiſcopal Conſtitutions alſo have been made to the ſame effect by <hi>Robert Winchelſey</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>That the Reader may underſtand the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples upon which theſe men acted, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine then preached amongſt them, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and believed, I have inferted in the Margin the Preamble of a Grant of King <hi>Stephens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118978:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">Porvenie ad audientiam noſtram, quod Mults in Dioceſsitua, decimas ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as integrasvel duaspartes ipſarum non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiis in quarum par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chiis hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant, vel ubi predia habent, &amp; à qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Eccleſiaſtica praecipiunt Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lvunt, ſed eas aliis, pro ſua di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribuunt voluntate: Cum igitur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniens eſſe videatur &amp; à ratione diſsimile, ut Ecclefiae quae ſpiritualia ſeminant, metere non debeant a ſuis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochianis temporalia &amp; habere, frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatituae Authoritate praeſentium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgemus ut liceat tibi ſuper hoc non obſtante contradictione vel appell atiene cujuſlibet, ſeu conſuetudo hactenus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervata, quod Canonicum fuerit, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare &amp; facere, quod Statueris per cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuram Eccleſiaſticam firmiter obligare. Nullt ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Confirmationis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Datum Lateran <hi>11.</hi> Nonas Iulii.</note>But notwithſtanding the many Laws, Canons, &amp; Decrees of Kings, Popes, Councils &amp; Biſhops, that every man ought to pay the tenth part of his encreaſe, yet was it left to the owner to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it where he pleaſed, which made ſo many rich Abbies and Monaſteries; and till the year 1200. or thereabouts, every one gave their tythes at their own pleaſure, which made Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third ſend his Decretal Epiſtle to the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> commanding him to enjoyn eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to pay his temporal Goods to thoſe that miniſtred ſpiritual things to them, which was enforced by Eccleſiaſtical cenſures; and this was the firſt beginning of general Parochial payment of tythes in <hi>England:</hi> I have inſerted the Popes own words in the Margin, as they are recorded by <hi>Cook</hi> in the ſecond part of his Inſtitutes, who ſaith, That becauſe the Popes Decree ſeemed reaſonable, it was admitted and enjoyned by the Law of the Nation, King and people being then papiſts.</p>
               <p>This Decree of the Pope receiving all poſſible aſſiſtance from the Biſhops and the Prieſts, in whoſe behalf it was made, did not onely in a ſhort time take away the peoples then deſired Right to give their tythes to thoſe that beſt deſerved them, but did alſo ſo much corrupt the Clergy, that in the time of <hi>R.</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Wick liffe</hi> our famous Reformer did make a heavy complaint to the Parliament, which in his own words I have inſerted for the Readers better ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Ah Lord God! where this be reaſon to conſtrain the poor people to finde a worldly Prieſt, ſometime unable both of life and ounning, in pomp and pride, covetiſe and envy, gluttoneſs, drunkenneſſe, and letchery, in ſimony and hereſie, with fat horſe and jolly, and gay Saddles and Bridles ringing by the way, and himſelf in coſtly clothes and pelure, and to ſuffer their Wives and Children, and their poor Neighbors perish for hunger, thirſt, and cold, and other miſchiefs of the world: Ah Lord Ieſu Chriſt, ſith within few years men paid their tythes and offerings at their own will, free to good men, and able to great Worship of God, to profit and fairneſs of holy Church fighting in earth; why it were lawful and needful that a worldly Prieſt should deſtroy this holy and approved cuſtom, conſtraining men to leave this freedom, turning Tythes and Offerings unto wicked uſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the meaning of theſe, and the practice of this Nation in this matter may the better be underſtood, it is needful to inform the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that when the Popes Doctrine was received in a Nation, that Nation was divided into ſo many Biſhopricks as were needful, and every Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick into ſo many pariſhes as were thought convenient, and pariſhes are but of late erection, and till then moſt <hi>Preachers</hi> were ſent out of tho
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118978:8"/>Monaſteries, and religious (ſo called) Houſes, and the people did at their own free will give their tythes and offerings where they pleaſed, which liberty they enjoyed till about the year 1200. And though it was generally believed that tythes ought to be paid, yet did no man claim any property therein, but every owner of the nine parts was required to give the tenth part to the Prieſt or poor, as due unto God.</p>
               <p>But now the Pope having ſet up Pariſhes, did enjoyne that a Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar prieſt canonically inſtituted, ſhould attend the ſervice of each pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; and that where tythes were not already ſetled, they ſhould be paid to the Pariſh-Prieſt, notwithſtanding any cuſtom to the contrary; the people then generally being Papiſts, did yeild obedience, as they durſt not do otherwiſe; and it may eaſily be ſuppoſed, that having perſwaded the people to pay tythes, it was no hard matter to appoint the perſon to whom they ſhould be given.</p>
               <p>Pariſhes being ſet up, Prieſts appointed, and tythes paid to them after fourty years poſſeſſion, what before was owned as the gift, was now claimed as a debt; and preſcription was pleaded by the prieſts as their juſt title; the people then ſeeing themſelves in a ſnare, began to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; but the imperious Pope (now in a great height of pride and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to uphold his Creature-Clergy) thundred out his Interdict a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Nation, excommunicaeted the King, frighted the Subjects with his Bulls ſtuft with Commination, and that againſt the very point of Arbitrary diſpoſal of tythes: And <hi>Rome</hi> now grown formidable, did highly inſult over Kings and Princes; wineſſe <hi>Frederick, Barbaroſſa, Hen.</hi> the 6th. and other Princes of the Empire; and the Stories of our <hi>H.</hi> 2. and K. <hi>Iohn,</hi> are obvious: And our <hi>Rich.</hi> the firſt to gratifie the Clergy for their exceeding liberality in contributing to his ranſom from captivity, with great favour gave them an indulgent Charter of their Liberties, and in this advantage of time the Canon-Laws gained ſuch force, that Parochial-payment came generally to be ſetled.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding our <hi>English</hi> Parliaments not willing wholly to forget the poor, for whoſe ſake tythes were chiefly given, did make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Laws that a convenient portion of the tythes ſhould be ſet apart for the maintenance of the poor of the pariſh for ever, <hi>R.</hi> 2.15.6. 4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. as the Statutes at large do witneſſe.</p>
               <p>The Pope having by theſe means brought in tythes, and made a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended title by preſcription, ſet up Courts to recover them, which were called Eccleſiaſtical Courts, where his own creatures were Judges, and here the poor people might eaſily underſtand what they might expect from them; yet he that did not pay, no great puniſhment could they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict on him, but excommunication out of their Church.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> by all means willing to favour his chiefeſt props, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his general Decree, could tell how to diſpenſe with his own Lands at his pleaſure, and therefore frequently did grant exemptions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118978:9"/>to divers Orders to free them from payment of tythes; witneſſe the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallers, Ciſtercians, Templers, and generally to all I ands held in the occupation of the called religious Perſons and Houſes, which is the ground of all thoſe mens claims who have bought the Lands of diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Monaſteries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſay they are tythe-free.</p>
               <p>When the Pope by colour of the Jewiſh Laws (by which tythes were given to the Levitical Prieſthood) had gained an univerſal payment of tythes to all his Clergy, in further imitation of that earthly Tabernacle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſets up a new building after the former pattern, and therefore to himſelf he claims firſt-fruits and tenths as a Succeſſor of the Jewiſh High-Prieſt; fins alſo he undertook to pardon. Cardinals alſo he appoints as Loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their Families; Myters they were on their heads, as <hi>Aaron,</hi> did; Synagogues they build, with Singers, Porters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and into the ſorm of the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſthood they transform themſelves, thereby wholly denying Chriſt Jeſus the end of Types and Figures, to be come in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Afterwards <hi>H.</hi> 8. King of <hi>England</hi> being a Papiſt, and believing the Popes Doctrine, as alſo did his Parliament, that tythes were due to God and Holy Church, made a Law that every one ſhould ſet out and pay his tythes.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing this is the great Law, and the firſt of our Parliament-Laws for tythes, and that upon which the reſt are grounded, I ſhall here inſert the Preamble of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foraſmuch as divers numbers of evil-diſpoſed perſons, having no reſpect to their dutyes to Almighty God, but againſt right and good conſcience have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to ſubstract and with-hold in ſome places the whole, and in ſome places great parts of their Tythes and Oblations, as well perſonal as predial, due unto God and Holy Church, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſecond Law in his time was alſo made to the like purpoſe, and in purſuance of the former; and great reaſon he had, and need there was for them; for having diſſolved many Monaſteries who had many tythes and Rectories appropriated to them, and either had them in his own hands, or ſold them to others, to be held as lay-poſſeſſions, and they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Law whereby to recover them, the Popes Laws not reaching to Lay-perſons (ſo called) he was neceſſitated to make new Laws to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the payment of them, which the better to colour over the matter, he makes in general terms, but ſtill reſtrains the tryal of tythes to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</p>
               <p>After him <hi>Edw.</hi> the ſixth, in purſuance of his Fathers Laws, and upon the ſame grounds makes another Law for the payment of predial and perſonal tythes, under penalty of trebble damages, who alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains the tryal to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts. Theſe Laws ſuppoſe, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118978:9"/>tythes were due to God and Holy Church, and therefore they require that every man do yeild and ſet out his tythes, as had been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed.</p>
               <p>In purſuance of theſe Laws ſome Ordinances were made in the time of the long Parliament, in the Exigences of the War, becauſe the Courts of Juſtice were obſtructed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And theſe are the ſubſtance of all our Engliſh Laws concerning Tythes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus generally and briefly run over the Laws and practices of tything, both abroad, and in this Nation, I ſhall give ſome hints of the Opinions of former times concerning tythes. About the yeare 1000. and 1200. after Chriſt, when tythes were generally preached up and claimed, great controverſie did ariſe between the Canomiſts and the Clergy by what immediate Law tythes were payable.</p>
               <p>The Canoniſts generally ground themſelves upon the Decrees and Canons of the Church, (ſo called) and on the Writings of <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe,</hi> and the reſt of the ancient Fathers, who ſay they are due by Divine Right.</p>
               <p>The Clergy of thoſe times were at difference amongſt themſelves, ſome of them ſaying, That tythes, <hi>quoad quotam partem,</hi> or as it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined part, is due onely by poſitive and Eccleſiaſtick Law; but <hi>quoad ſubſtantiam ſuam,</hi> or as it devotes a competent part to be allowed for the maintenance of the Miniſtry, is due by Divine Law; and that the tenth part was decreed by the Church, <hi>per vim ejus exemplarem,</hi> or by imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Jewiſh State, and not <hi>per vim obligativam,</hi> or any continuing force of it under the Goſpel; and that the Church was not bound to this part, but freely might as wel have ordained the payment of a 9th. or 8th. according to the various opportunity. This was taught by <hi>Hales, Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Henricus de Grandavo, Ride Media villa, Cardinal Caj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian, Io. Mayer, Snarez, Malder,</hi> and others, who ſay it is the common Opinion of the greateſt part of the Clergy of that time, and that the tenth part was rather ceremonial then moral.</p>
               <p>Here alſo was made a diſtinction, and many ſaid that predial and mixt tythes were due by the divine Eccleſiaſtick Law; but perſonal tythes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Decrees of the Church; but <hi>Hales</hi> ſaid that tythes, as well perſonal as predial, are in the precept <hi>Quoad ſubſtantiam,</hi> but neither <hi>Quoad quotam;</hi> and therefore in <hi>Venice</hi> and other Cities, where no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial tythes are, a perſonal tythe is required by the poſitive Law of the Church, by vertue of the ſubſtance (not ceremony) of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>Another Opininion (and that owned by many) was drawn from the former Doctrine, which concluded, That ſeeing tythes as the <hi>quota pars,</hi> were not enjoined by the command of God, therefore they were meer Alms, or as what <hi>debito Charitatis,</hi> not <hi>debito juſticiae,</hi> was to be diſpenſed.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118978:10"/>Of this Opinion were the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who both began about the year 1210. and by their Doctrine got many tythes to be given to their Monaſteries, and that whatſoever was given to the four Orders of <hi>Mendicant Fryars,</hi> was a ſufficient diſcharge from the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>And our famous Reformers, <hi>Iohn Wickliffe, Walter Brute, Will. Thorp,</hi> and others, whoſe Arguments are at large in <hi>Fox</hi> his <hi>Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> did in their dayes bear their teſtimony againſt tythes, for which ſome of them ſuffered in flames.</p>
               <p>Agreeing herewith are the Articles of the <hi>Bohemians</hi> publiſhed near 300. years ſince, wherein a divine right to tythes ſince the Goſpel is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed; whereupon alſo long ſince they took all their temporalties from their Miniſters; And before <hi>Wickliffes</hi> time <hi>Gerardus Sagarellus</hi> was of the ſame mind. And the great <hi>Eraſmus</hi> alſo ſaid, That the common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting of tythes by the Clergy of his time, was no better then Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
               <p>Having thus briefly run over the Doctrines, Decrees, Practices and Opinions concerning tythes; I ſhall make ſome ſhort obſervations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that the Reader may underſtand whereunto they tend, and then proceed to the matter as it concerns us at this day, wherein he will finde the knowledge of theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> things will be uſeful.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That amongſt the Jews tythes were paid to the Levites that did the common ſervices of the Tabernacle and Temple, and not to the ſons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> the prieſts; for they had onely a tenth part out of the tythes; and therefore he that pleads for tythes from the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Laws of tything, had need conſider how the payment of tythes to Miniſters, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to the payment of tythes to the Levites, who were not prieſts, nor were to touch or meddle with that holy Office, leaſt they dyed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That amongſt the Jews no outward Law was appointed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of tythes, but he that did not pay them robbed God, and by him onely was puniſhed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the tythes were not for the Levites onely, but for the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the fatherleſſe, and the widow, who were to eat thereof, and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That when the Levitical prieſthood was changed by the coming of Chriſt Jeſus, the law for tything was alſo changed, as <hi>Paul</hi> writ to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> for it is evident, that in the beginning of the Church, for the firſt 300. years, while the purity and ſimplicity of the Goſpel was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, no tythes were paid amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That as the myſterie of iniquity began to work, and mens imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations were taught inſtead of the Doctrine of Chriſt, divers men fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their ground from <hi>Moſes</hi> writings, began to preach that tythes again ought to be paid.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That thoſe that firſt preached up tythes, preſſed the payment of of them, not for the maintenance of a Miniſtry onely, but chiefly for proviſion for the poor and needy.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118978:10"/>
7. That in the firſt practice of the payment of tythes, they were not paid as tythes, but as free offerings at the bounty of the giver, and not as anſwering any law that required the tenth part, and ſo more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were called offerings, then tythes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That notwithſtanding any Doctrines preached, it was not a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Doctrine that tythes ought to be paid till about the year 1000. that the Pope had ſet up his Authority, and uſurped Dominion over the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt parts of Europe, and almoſt all Emperors, Kings, and Princes brought in ſubjection to him and his innovated ſuperſtirions.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That notwithſtanding the ſtrict commands of the Pope, no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward compulſary Law was made by the Pope or his Councils to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force any to pay tythes, but onely their excommunication.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That tythes were alwayes accounted an Eccleſiaſtical duty, and therefore by Eccleſiaſtical Courts were tryed and judged; and til the diſſolution of Abbeys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were never called a Civil Right.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That tythes were brought in as a duty owing unto God, and were ſo required and enforced; and therefore all laws made for the payment of tythes, takes that for their ground, and not any civil property or right in him that claims them.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That till the year 1200. or thereabouts, it was the common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice for every one to beſtow his tythes where he pleaſed.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That from ſuch Arbitrary diſpoſitions, Abbeys and Monaſteries came to be ſo richly endowed with Tythes and Rectories.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That all exemptions from payment of tythes came from the Pope.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That firſt fruits and tenths are but a late innovation, and claimed by the Pope as Succeſſor to the Jewiſh High-Prieſt, as <hi>Cook</hi> in the third part of his <hi>Inſtitutes</hi> alſo teſtifies</p>
               <p n="16">16. That tythes are the ſame thing, whether claimed by an Abbey, or Impropriator, or a Prieſt, and ſtand upon the ſame ground and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and differ nothing but in the perſon that poſſeſſeth them.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Here alſo the declining State of the Church to corruption &amp; error may be clearly diſcerned &amp; traced; for as the power of truth was loſt, ſo was the fruit thereof, which cauſed ſuch earneſt preſſing to needful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions, &amp; when that would not ſerve, Laws &amp; Decrees were made to force them: But in the beginning it was not ſo; for while the purity and ſimplicity of the Goſpel was retained, there needed no preſſing; for their charity then abounded not onely to the tenth part, but far greater parts, as the needs of the Church required.</p>
               <p n="18">18. That the right of tythes was never cleared, but remained in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie even amongſt the greateſt Papiſts, and in all ages there were thoſe that withſtood the payment of them: And many of the Martyrs for that, amongſt other things, ſuffered in flames.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118978:11"/>
Theſe things thus premiſed, I ſhall briefly ſtate the great Caſe and Queſtion at this day chiefly controverted concerning tythes, as claimed and paid in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether any perſon have a true and legal property in the tenth part of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans encreaſe, now commonly called tythes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The terms are plain, and need no opening; yet it is needful to declare why the Caſe is thus ſtated; for the great Queſtion rather ſeems to be, <hi>Whether tythes be not due at this day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That may be due to another wherein yet he may have no legal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, as Cuſtom, Tribute, Taxes, which are to be paid becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the State; and though Law and Equity obliges the payment, yet is no diſtinct property in him that commands; and ſo tythes may be ſuppoſed to be due, becauſe ſo many Laws have been made for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, though the perſon that claims them may have no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt or property therein, other then is derived from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>But now in <hi>England</hi> tythes are not onely claimed by vertue of divers Laws, but alſo as being a diſtinct property, ſevered from the property of the nine parts.</p>
               <p>And if this could clearly be evinced, all ſcruples of conſcience were anſwered; for if a true and legal property be in another perſon to the tenth part of any encreaſe, I ought in conſcience to yeild and ſet it forth, becauſe it is not mine; and then the Name of tythe, as having in any meaſure relation to the Jewiſh prieſthood or popiſh Clergy, were at an end, but as a debt it ought to be truly paid to the proprietor.</p>
               <p>Many things have been ſaid, and much written to prove ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, the ſubſtance whereof, as far as hath come to my knowledge, I ſhall briefly ſum up under theſe general Heads; as alſo the grounds of thoſe who claim them to be due, and yet plead no property, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leſſer, may be fully included and anſwered in the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="claims">
               <head>Several Claims made for tythes, and a legal property therein, ſet down and anſwered.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt claims tythes to be due <hi>jure divine,</hi> and produce the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> for it it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others ſay, that as to the <hi>quota pars,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the tenth part) tythes are not now due by the Law of God: onely the equity of the Law is ſtill of force, which obligeth to afford a competent maintenance for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, but doth not bind to the certain quantity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Others there are who plead the Decrees, Canons, and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of General Councils, Popes, Biſhops, Convocations, and theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118978:11"/>ſay that tythes are due <hi>jure Eccleſiaſtico.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnder theſe ſeveral Claims, or ſome of them, have tythes been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and paid, ſince the dark night of Apoſtacy overſpread the earth under the Papal power, till the Popes Supremacy and Religion was caſt off in <hi>England;</hi> and where the popiſh Religion is profeſſed, they are now by the ſame demanded and paid.</p>
               <p>But now of late in <hi>England</hi> now Claims are made, and the old pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ſeem too much to ſavour of the popiſh Leven, and therefore a humane right is pleaded, which I ſhall briefly bring under theſe few heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some plead the gifts of Kings and Princes, who were Rulers of the people, as <hi>Ethelwoſph,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others plead the temporal Laws of Kings, Parliaments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Others plead the particular gifts, appropriation, conſecration, or donation of thoſe who were former owners of the Land.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Others plead preſcription and a legal right by their poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Others plead a legal right by purchaſe.</p>
               <p>And beſides theſe, I never heard or read of any other pretence for tythes, though I have diligently for two years, and more, laboured to inform my ſelf fully what could be alledged for them.</p>
               <p>To begin with the firſt, Thoſe that ſay tythes are due by Divine Right.</p>
               <p>Some of them ſay, <hi>That the Law given to Iſrael for payment of tenths to the Tribe of Levi, doth alſo oblige Chriſtians to pay tenths to their Miniſters, as ſucceeding in the Prieſts Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſuch it is clearly anſwered, That the prieſthood which had a commandment to take tythes being changed by Chriſt Jeſus, there is made of neceſſity alſo a change of the Law; and now the prieſthood is no more committed to the natural off-ſpring of <hi>Levi,</hi> or any other tribe, but to Chriſt Jeſus the unchangeable prieſthood, whoſe Kingdom ſtands not in figures and carnal Ordinances, but is the Subſtance of what that was but a figure: And it is clear the primitive Church were aſſur'd of it, who for ſome hundreds of years, and till the myſterie of Iniquity began to work, never called for the payment of tythes, as is before plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved.</p>
               <p>And how doth a Goſpel Miniſtry ſucceed to the Levites, who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved tythes but were not prieſts; much more colour had the Quiriſters, Singing-men, and the reſt of the Rabble brought into the late Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals, to claim them, and onely to pay out a tenth part to the prieſts, as the Levites did.</p>
               <p>Others ſay, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>paid tythes to</hi> Melchiſedec, <hi>which was before the Levitical Prieſthood; and Chriſt Ieſus is made a Prieſt after the Order of</hi> Melchiſedec.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118978:12"/>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> returning from the ſlaughter of the Kings, was met by <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> who brought him bread and wine, and <hi>Abraham</hi> gave him the tenth of the tythes, but what is this to the payment of tythes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it oblige the Souldiers? for it doth not appear that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid the tenth part of his own increaſe; nor doth it appear that <hi>Abraham</hi> gave the tenth part at any other time; and how will this prove a yearly payment of tythes to Miniſters?</p>
               <p>And what if <hi>Iacob</hi> gave tythes? how are either of theſe examples more binding then any other of the good acts that either of theſe holy men did?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If it be ſaid, that Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, <hi>ye tythe min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. theſe things ye ought not to leave undone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's anſwered, that Jeſus Chriſt then ſpoke to the Jewes in the time when the Levitical prieſthood was not ended, who were bound by the Law ſo long as it was of force, till he was offered up, and ſaid, <hi>It is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But though Divine Right hath been of long pretended, few are now left who will onely ſtand to it, and the generalitie both of Lawyers, Prieſts and people are of a contrary minde.</p>
               <p>For if <hi>Tythes</hi> be abſolutely due by the Law of God, no cuſtome, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, preſcription, priviledge, or popiſh diſpenſation, can acquit from payment of the utmoſt peny of the tenth part; but ſcarce the tenth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in England payeth <hi>Tyth</hi> in kinde, and many plead they are <hi>tythe</hi>-free, and pay none at all, and others very ſmall matters; and ſo the greateſt part of the people of England deny <hi>Tythes</hi> to be due by Gods Law.</p>
               <p>Again, if <hi>Tythes</hi> be due by the Law of God, then is it to the end for which they were commanded, for the <hi>Levites,</hi> the <hi>Strangers,</hi> the <hi>Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> and the <hi>Widows;</hi> all therefore who plead for <hi>Tythes</hi> by Divine Right, muſt not pay them to an <hi>Impropriator;</hi> for by Gods Law he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not claim, neither ought any Impropriator of that minde to receive them.</p>
               <p>And of late yeers, it was by <hi>Rolls,</hi> Chief Juſtice, adjudged in the Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bench, That <hi>Tythes</hi> are not now due by the Law of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To the next, thoſe that plead the Equity of the Law is ſtill of force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe plead not for <hi>Tythes</hi> properly, but for a comfortable mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and by way of <hi>Tythes,</hi> as they ſuppoſe moſt convenient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And theſe bring many Scriptures in the New Teſtament, that he that labors is worthy of his hire; he that preacheth the Goſpel ought to live of the Goſpel; let him that is taught communicate to him that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118978:12"/>
And to ſuch I ſay, that not onely the Equitie of the Leviticall Law for <hi>Tything,</hi> the Doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus and his Apoſtles do binde, but even from natural thinge we are largely taught our duty therein; <hi>No man muzleth the mouth of the Oxe,</hi> and <hi>no man goeth a warfare at his own charge;</hi> and <hi>he that plants a vinyard, eats the fruit thereof:</hi> And herein it is agreed, that the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who are called to his ſervice and labour in the Word, ought to be comfortably provided for, that they go not a warfare at their own charge.</p>
               <p>But this doth not require that the world (which lies waſte as a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and is not of the Vinyard) ſhould contribute, much leſs be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to give a certain portion of the fruits of their labours towards the maintenance of Chriſts Miniſters.</p>
               <p>And theſe grant, that every man is the ſole owner of his own labour and poſſeſſion; and though by another he may not be compelled, for ſuch ſacrifice God abhors, yet ought every one freely to glorifie God with his ſubſtance, to ſtrengthen the weak hands, and feeble knees, and to give to him that teacheth, thoſe things that are needfull, and ſuch cheerfull givers God accepts.</p>
               <p>And this leaves every one free to give to him that teacheth, not bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the maintenance of thoſe who have leſſe need then the giver, or of thoſe who are transformed as Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, who have the form, but want the power, who teach for filthy lucre, keeping ever learning, but cannot bring to the knowledge of the truth.</p>
               <p>And of ſuch as Chriſt Jeſus ſent forth, he alwayes took care, and they never wanted, but they reaped the fruits of their labour, and eat the fruits of their own Vinyards which they had planted, &amp; by the Churches who were gathered out of the world, were they maintained to preach the Goſpel to th world, unto whom they would not make the Goſpel chargeable or burthenſom, which was their glory and their Crown.</p>
               <p>And herewith let all our now called Churches be proved and tryed, who ſeparate from the world, and yet many of them receive pay and wages for their teachers from the world, who ſend none at their own coſt to preach to the world.</p>
               <p>And here our Rulers ſhould learn wiſdom to with-hold their hands from upholding any with their worldly Sword, and compelling others to maintain them, and to leave Chriſts Kingdom to his own Rule; who is Lord of the Harveſt, and ſends forth labourers, and hath ſpirit to put upon them; who ſends forth the-Fiſher-men, the Shepherds, the Herdſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the tillers of the ground, and the keepers of flocks, who ſpeake plain words that wiſe men cannot underſtand who are wiſe in the worlds wiſdom, gathered in Schools, whither they are ſent to learn a trade, thereby to get their livings; and in the time of popery they ſtudyed the popiſh Doctrine, and then preached them to others; and in the time of prelacy they changed to a new form: And when that was laid aſide,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118978:13"/>
                  <hi>Presbytery</hi> was ſet up, and then ſuch the Vniverſities ſent forth; and ſince <hi>Independency</hi> was preferred, great ſtore of them are ſpread abroad; and look what pleaſeth them beſt that have the greateſt livings in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that is the moſt cryed up, and moſt ſtudyed and preached; and here is the ſpring of our Teachers, the Vniverſities; and theſe ſay that <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> are the original, which they go thither to learn, that they may underſtand what Chriſt ſpoke, and the Apoſtles preached: But the <hi>Hebrews</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> who heard them ſpeake in their own Language, could not underſtand their Doctrine, for it ſeemed fooliſhneſſe to them; and theſe by their original are in no better ſtate, nor nearer to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Goſpel: And let our Rulers conſider, that Chriſts love to the world, for whom he dyed, is not abated; neither is his ſpirit dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; nor his powde ſhortened, that he will not, or cannot, ſend forth, and fit Miniſters for his ſervice, or that he needs Vniverſities to inſtruct, or Magiſtrates to provide maintenance for thoſe he ſends forth. And let them look to their own kingdom, the world, therein to puniſh &amp; reſtrain the evil, &amp; to encourage &amp; protect the good; &amp; then all would be agreed, and the Nation kept in peace, every one enjoying his true liberty and freedom: For in this it is aſſented, that the Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus who ſowe unto us ſpiritual things, ſhould reap of our temporals: But here is the difference; firſt, That our conſciences muſt be our judge who thoſe Miniſters are, and no other mans direction; for to the conſcience were Chriſts Miniſters alwayes made manifeſt, and not approved with the reaſon and wiſdom of man. Secondly, That our gift muſt be free, and by no mans compulſion.</p>
               <p>Would not this eaſe the Magiſtrate of much trouble that he makes to himſelf, and be more acceptable to God and man? for who hath made him a Judge in theſe things?</p>
               <p>A third ſort plead the Decrees, Canons, Conſtitutions of General Councils, Popes, Biſhops, Convocations.</p>
               <p>To ſuch I ſhall onely ſay, that for the firſt 800. years after Chriſt, no Canon or Decree was made by general Council, nor was it then deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Church (as 'twas called) what part every man ſhould pay. And the firſt eight General Councils do not ſo much as ſpeak of the name of tythes, and that was till about 1000. years; and then about that time it came to be received and believed that tythes ought to be paid; yet in <hi>England,</hi> as well as other Nations, every man might have given his tythe where he pleaſed, till about the year 1200. as is already proved. But I need not ſay much to theſe, few being of this mind, but thoſe who own the Pope for their Head, we having in <hi>England</hi> denyed and caſt off his Supremacy, though in this matter of tythes, and many other things, we ſtill feel his power amongſt us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118978:13"/>
And now having briefly gone over the ſubſtance of what is pleaded for a Divine of Eccleſiaſtick right, I come next to what is pretended for a humane Right.</p>
               <p>And the firſt ſort pleads the gifts of Kings, as <hi>Ethelwolph,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To theſe I anſwer, If they could prove the whole Land had been the particular poſſeſſion of any ſuch King, they ſaid ſomething, though that would not juſtifie the taking tythes from all the people, as ſhall be more fully proved hereafter. But by what right could he give the tenth part of the encreaſe and fruits of the labours of all the people of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who had no legal property therein? It was an eaſie matter when the Popes Emiſſaries had taught the people that tythes were due to God and them, and had perſwaded Kings and Nobles that Heaven might be purchaſed by then works, to procure from them the gift of that which was not theirs, the poor peoples tythes; eſpecially conſidering the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were of the ſame mind, and as zealous of all the popiſh ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as themſelves, and every one ſtriving who ſhould therein moſt excel; witneſſe thoſe many rich Abbeys and Monaſteries lately in this Land. But if that K. <hi>Ethelwolphs</hi> Grant be the foundation of tythes, then how many ſucceeding Kings, and Biſhops, and others, have violated his Deed by appropriating them to Abbeys, Monaſteries, and ſuch like Houſes? And how hath all Ages ſince <hi>Ethelwolphs,</hi> taken upon themſelve the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of tythes, without any relation to what he did? which ſhewes clearly, That neither Kings, Parliaments, nor prople did ever take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound by his Grant: But the folly and vanity of this Argument will more plainly appear hereafter.</p>
               <p>The next, and thoſe which ſeem to have the ſtrongeſt plea, do urge the temporal Laws of Kings and Parliaments, and ſay, by the Law they have as good property in tythes, as any man hath in his Lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſuch I ſay, The Law doth not give any man a property ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in land, or tythes, or any other thing, but onely doth conſerve to every man his property which he hath in his land and poſſeſſions, either by gift, purchaſe; or diſcent, and ſecure him from the injury or violence of another.</p>
               <p>But let us not be deceived with a new pretence, lately taken up to delude the ſimple minds of a legal property, and a civil right, for that is but a ſhift; and it matters not what any ſay, or now pretend concerning the right of tythes, when they ſee their other claims will not ſerve the turn; but let us hear what the Makres of the Laws ſay of them, thoſe from whom they claim; and paſſing by the <hi>Saxon</hi> times, and K. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe who were in the mid-night of popery, let us come to <hi>H.</hi> 8. who caſt off the Pope, and upon whoſe Law all others that were ſince made are builded; and in the preamble of the Act it is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That tythes are due to God and holy Church,</hi> and they blame men for being ſo wicked as not to pay them; and therefore that Law is made, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118978:14"/>here is the ground of the Law, not any property or civil right in prieſts or others; and therefore if the Law require them as due by Divine Right, he that ſaith they are onely due by humane right, cannot claim them, nor ought to recover them by that law, for he claims them by another right; and for any man to claim that by humane right, from humane law, which commands them as due by divine right, is but a meer deceit. And that law of <hi>H.</hi> 8. and the reſt, did upon any civil ground ſet up, or conſtitute the payment of tythes, but takes it for granted, <hi>that tythes are due to God and holy Church;</hi> and therefore the foundation of the law being taken away, <hi>that they are not due to God and holy Church,</hi> the law falls to the ground; for the law not making them due, but ſuppoſing them due by a former right, if they were not ſo due, the law cannot be binding.</p>
               <p>That tythes were never till now of late pretended a civil right, is plain; for as they were impoſed by the Pope, ſo were they tryable in his courts; and thoſe very laws made by late Parliaments, did appoint them to be tryed in the Eccleſiaſtical courts, and reſtrained the temporal Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Acts themſelves teſtifie.</p>
               <p>But what is the property that is now claimed? is it in a perſon? that cannot be, for the prieſt hath them not till he enter his Office, and when he parts with that, he loſeth his tythes: So the prieſt hath no property, but his Office; and what is that? it was a popiſh Office when tythes were firſt paid to it, and how comes the property to continue now the Office is laid aſide, and the Pope that ſet them up? But how can a civil right or property be pretended, when the Author was the Pope? The end for a called ſpiritual Office, and recovered in an Eccleſiaſtical called Court, are not theſe covers grown too ſhort?</p>
               <p>And in the Act of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. tythes are called <hi>Spiritual Gifts:</hi> and there of impropriate tythes ſold after the diſſolution, its ſaid, they are now made temporal: And before that time it was never heard that tythes were called a temporal right.</p>
               <p>But it's further ſaid, <hi>Theſe Laws were made by Parliaments, the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the people: And though tythes were not due before, yet they might give tythes, becauſe their own, they being the body of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This would ſuppoſe a particular conſecration, or donation of the people, not onely as in their Legiſlative capacity, to bind themſelves by a Law, but by a particular Act of Free-gift: but it's plain, the Act ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended any ſuch thing, for it gives nothing, but commands what was before.</p>
               <p>And as to the Law it ſelf, and all other Laws of Kings, Parliaments, Popes, Councils, Biſhops, and what ever elſe was by any man made for the payment of tythes ſince Chriſt Jeſus came in the fleſh, joyned all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, how do they all, or any of them bind the conſcience? for if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118978:14"/>tythes be not due by the Law of God, as is herein proved, and almoſt generally granted: Who hath ſet them up? the law of man at beſt; And who is man that makes a law in the place where God diſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled his own command? is it better to obey man then God? or is man grown wiſer then his Maker? Who put this power into the hand of man to raiſe a compulſary maintenance for Miniſters? That any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have power to make any binding law for the maintenance of thoſe they call Miniſters, for doing a work which they call Worſhip of God, and force the people to ſubmit to it, the clear light of this age doth generally condemn; for they are much more like to ſet up and maintain thoſe who are contrary to Chriſt, then Chriſts Miniſters, who never looked for, nor durſt own ſuch a way of proviſion. Will any ſay they have power? from whom had they it? Is it derived from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? that cannot be. Have they any other power committed to them? how is it? as they are Magiſtrates; If ſo, the <hi>Turk,</hi> and all infidel Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates have the like? Or is it as they are Chriſtian Magiſtrates? then may not <hi>France, Spain, &amp;c.</hi> claim the ſame? for what Nation in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> will not ſay they have a Chriſtian Magiſtracy, though far the greater part of them be <hi>Papiſts?</hi> And may not a <hi>Papiſt</hi> by as good right require and compel maintenance for his Miniſters, as <hi>H.</hi> 8. or any other could, or can do? But that I may not be miſtaken, as if I went about to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Magiſtrates power to raiſe Taxes, Seſſements, or other charges, for the ſervice and defence of the Nation, it is needful to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe things that are called civil, and ſuch as are called ſpiritual: For civil ends and uſes the people may give power to their Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to raiſe moneys, or any other civil thing, becauſe in ſuch things they are their own Maſters: But in matters of Religion and ſpiritual things, no man can give power unto another to impoſe any thing upon himſelf, or his neighbor, for in thoſe things every one is to be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto God, and to ſtand and fall to his own Maſter. And thus we give unto God the things that are Gods, and unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are his, paying tribute to whom tribute is due. But as for all laws made in the will of man, in the things of God, and their heavy puniſhments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon ſuch as cannot for conſcience ſake conform unto them, they reach not the conſcience, and therefore make no ſinne againſt God.</p>
               <p>And as concerning the laws of K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. and <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. it may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſome of them were made by a Popiſh King and Parliament, and the reſt, in the glimmerings of light, when men were but ſeen as trees; and therefore to make their laws a Rule for this day of clear and Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine light, ſavours too much of the old Popiſh Spirit, and is a ſhame to our reformation: And if it be ſaid Papiſts might, and did make good laws; It's true, in temporal things they did, but not in things of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein they are differenced from us, becauſe <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118978:15"/>
But were the law juſt in commanding tythes, can it be equal to give double or trebble damage where they are not paid? If any man be oweing a juſt and due debt, no more by law can be recovered, but what the Debt is, beſides the charges of the law: How cruel therefore are theſe Laws and Ordinances, which in a matter of ſo much juſt ſcruple, require and impoſe the double or trebble value? And how unrighteous are all ſuch perſons, as by force of ſuch laws receive them? for if tythes were due, is therefore the trebble value due, becauſe the law hath made that penalty? Where is equity or juſtice in either? The <hi>Pope</hi> and his Adherents did onely excommunicate the refuſer till he conformed; and till theſe late laws, ſuch penalties as impriſonment and trebble damage were never known. And here what was by our forefathers ſuperſtition (whom we look back at as afar off, and pitty) begun in ignorance, we build up, and confirm with tyrannie, and inſtead of their Rods, make to our ſelves Scorpions.</p>
               <p>But herein is not all, but the law requires every man to ſet out the tenth, and ſo makes him a voluntary Agent in that againſt which his conſcience teſtifies, which is moſt cruel and unrighteous; and he that cannot do ſo, they ſue and hale before Courts and Magiſtrates, and there they get judgement of trebble damage, and by that judgement frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take five-fold, yea ſometime ten-fold the value: Shall not theſe things render this age which ſo much pretends to reformation, contemptible to future generations? and for theſe things ſhall not even <hi>Papists</hi> riſe up in judgement againſt us, and condemn us?</p>
               <p>But how is it that any law for tythes is now executed? do not all laws and ſtatutes for tythes reſtrain the tryal of them to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and prohibit the temporal Courts from medling with them. And ſince the Eccleſiaſtical Courts are deſtroyed, who have power to give judgement for tythes? no temporal Judge proceeding according to the laws for tything: How is it then that ſo many perſons are ſued, proſecuted, and unjuſtly vexed for tythes in all the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and not onely ſo, but in the Sherifts Court, and other pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Courts in the countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If it be ſaid, <hi>The Statute gives double damages and costs, and no Court being appointed where that shall be recovered, it muſt be ſuppoſed to be the Common-Law Courts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, by asking of what muſt they give the double or trebble da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, ſeeing they are reſtrained from trying for the ſingle value? if they cannot judge the one, how can they award the other? will they condemn an acceſſary before they try the principal? what is this but to make the law a Noſe of Wax, or any thing, to uphold another un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118978:15"/>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> It will be ſaid, <hi>Iuſtices of Peace have power:</hi> It may be ſo by an Ordinance, but no Act of Parliament, which is the Law of <hi>England;</hi> and that they do it, many poor people feel; for generally they give treb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble damages for all manner of tythes, when as the Statute gave but double, and coſts, and that onely for predial tythes: And they uſually execute their precepts by ſuch perſons as will do it effectually, who take generally five times more then the value, which they prize, and ſell far under the worth; and he that cannot comply with their cruelty, and confeſſe their judgement juſt, by accepting back what they will return, doth frequently ſuffer five or ſix-fold, yea often ten-fold damage? And here the fingers of the Juſtices are too often found by conſciencious men, far more heavy then the loynes of the Law, nay more then of the old Eccleſiaſtical Courts, or the Pope himſelf, who hath no ſuch penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. I write what I can prove by manifold inſtances.</p>
               <p>Though theſe oppreſſions be many and great, yet are they not all that this age exerciſes; for by a new device, under pretence that Prieſts are not able to pay tenths to the Protector, unleſſe every man pay them their tythes, they ſue men for all manner of tythes by <hi>English</hi> Bill in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and there would force them upon their oaths to declare what tythes they have, when as in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts the Ordinary might not examine a man upon his own oath concerning his own tythe: And here ſuch as either make conſcience of ſwearing, which Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids, or cannot themſelves tell what tythe they had, are caſt into priſon for contempt, where they may lie as long as they live, no Law in the Nation reaching them any relief: And divers upon this account have long lain in the Fleet, &amp; yet are there; and I believe above a hundred ſuits are in the Exchequer depending, and proceedings ſtopt at this point, the hearts of the very Officers of the Court relenting with pitty towards ſuch numbers of poor men brought thither very Term from the moſt remore parts of the Nation, and ſome of them not for above twelve pence; ſuch mercileſſe cruelty lodges in the hearts of many, if not the moſt of our pretended Goſpel Miniſters.</p>
               <p>Oh ſhameful reformation! What! compel a man himſelf to ſet out the tythe of his own Goods to maintain a Hireling-Prieſt, it may be one openly prophane, and ſo make him ſin againſt his own conſcience, or take from him thrice, or rather five times as much! and not onely ſo, but to force him to ſwear what tythes he had, or commit him to priſon, there to lie without hope of relief; doth not the cry of theſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions reach through Palace-Walls, and enter Parliament-doors? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they reach the Gates of Heaven: And though man have forgotten his fair promiſes, God will in due time break theſe bands, and ſend re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief another way. Oh curſed firſt fruits and tenths, the ſuperſtitious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique of Popery, and wages of unrighteouſneſſe, the cauſe and cover of all theſe Exchequer Suits, and of moſt of theſe miſchiefs! Muſt we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118978:16"/>ſtill have Prieſts and tythes? then may we not wiſh for old Prieſts, and old Eccleſiaſtical Courts? for much more moderation was in them, and even Papiſts would bluſh at our cruelties. Did but the Magiſtiate ſee what havock is made in the North, what driving of Goods, the Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en out of the plow, the Cows from poor and indigent children, what carrying of Pots, Pans, and Kettles, yea and fetching the very clothes of poor peoples Beds, he would either be aſhamed of ſuch Juſtices, or ſuch Prieſts, or Tythes, or of them all. Such inſtances I could give as would make the Readers ears to tingle; and he that cannot believe me, let him ſend into <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and he ſhall meet with ſew that cannot inform him of it; or do but let him go a little after Harveſt, and he may find the Juſtices ſo buſie, as if they had little other work to be doing. But whither have I digreſſed? let me return to heare what the next can ſay.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And theſe plead the gift of thoſe that were formerly poſſeſſors of the Land, and ſay, <hi>Thoſe that pay tythes, do but that which their Anceſtors juſtly charged upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſuch I anſwer, That it's true, many Anceſtors gave tythes which of them were required, as before hath been declared; but what is that to us? or how are we thereby bound? Did ever any man in any Deed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of his Land, expreſſe any ſuch gift, or made any exception of tythes? I never ſaw or heard of ſuch a thing; and let thoſe who can find ſuch reſervations, make their claim; but I believe it will not be in <hi>England.</hi> That which this ſort pleads, ſeems to make a ground for a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct property; for if there be a property, it muſt of neceſſity ariſe from him that was the true owner, and had power to charge himſelf and his poſterity; and theſe ſay they <hi>have as good right to the tenth part as the owner hath to the nine,</hi> and <hi>that he never purchaſed it,</hi> and the like. Vnto all which I anſwer, That though it were true, &amp; could be proved that mine Anceſtors gave tythes, and that for ever, yet am I not thereby bound to pay them, or ſtand any way chargeable with them. It's true, when they were owners of Land they might themſelves yeild and ſet forth what part of their encreaſe they pleaſed, or might have given the tenth, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other part of their Land, as they would, or they might have charged upon the Land what Rent they liked; but they could not charge their poſterity with that which was no way theirs, nor which in any true ſence, conſtruction, or underſtanding, they could be ſaid to have any property in, and which is not paid by reaſon of that which is derived from them; for tythe is neither paid of I and, nor by reaſon of the Land, but is paid by reaſon of the encreaſe or renewing, and therefore the Doctrines of the old Fathers, the Statute of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and ſo the Popiſh Laws for tythes do as well require the payment of the tenth part of mens profits and gain, whetherby Trade, Commerce, or Merchandize, as of the fruits of the earth, yea the tenth part of wages and all perſonal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118978:16"/>though not raiſed immediately by Land: And ſurely no man will ſay that he payes tythe of theſe becauſe his Anceſtor charged him with them; nor will any man allow that another perſon by any gift of his Anceſtor, can have another diſtinſt property in the tenth part of the fruit of his labours; and the caſe is the ſame as to all tythes, whether predial, perſonal, or mixt; if I ſit ſtill and plough not, no Corn will grow: If I ſit ſtill, and work not, no profit will riſe; ſo that it's my labour, my dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and induſtry that raiſeth the tythe, and in my power it is to make it leſſe or more; and ſometimes, yea often it falls out, that the tythe of Corn is thrice more worth then the yearly value of the Land on which it grows; and herein tythe of Corn is far more hard and unequal then perſonal tythes; for the one payes but the tenth, all charges deducted; the other payes the tenth of charges and all.</p>
               <p>Mine Anceſtor could not charge me with that which doth not accrue by reaſon of that which I have from him; nor am I bound becauſe mine Anceſtor left me Land, to pay tythe, which is not paid by reaſon of the Land, but of the encreaſe, unto which I am no more tyed by Law, then he is who hath encreaſe without Land. If I have Land, and no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, I pay no tythes: If I have encreaſe, though no Land, I ought by Law to pay tythes. If I husband my Land ſo as the encreaſe of it is not to be ſevered, no tythe can be recovered of it; and therefore if I pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture my Land, no tythe ſhall be paid for the graſſe which is eaten unſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but onely a rate-tythe for that which doth depaſture on it, which makes it plain, that tythe is not paid by reaſon of the Land, but of the Stock; and in that alſo it lies in my power to make the tythe much, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or nothing, if I plow and ſowe Corn, the tenth part of the encreaſe is generally more worth then the Land on which it grows, which comes by the Land which deſcends from the Anceſtor, but becauſe of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, won by the great charge, induſtry, and labour of the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. If I paſture my ground with Sheep that yeilds a Fleece, the tythe will be conſiderable, though not ſo much as by Corn. If I paſture with Cows or breeding Cattle, a much-leſſe tythe is paid: And if I eat with Horſes and barren Cattle, a ſmall and inconſiderable rate is onely required<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though in few places of the Nation would that be recovered in the times of greateſt height of popiſh Laws. But if I plant Wood, and let it ſtand for Timber; or if I ſtore my Land with Beaſts which be <hi>ferae naturae,</hi> wherein there is no perſonal property, no tythe ſhall be paid. Or if I will let my Land lye waſte, (which may be ſuppoſed, becauſe it may be done) or will eat my Meadow, or Corn ſtanding, no tythe can be required. All theſe inſtances manifeſt that tythe hath ſtill relation to tlie ſtock and perſonal eſtate, and not to the Land; and is paid by reaſon of the ſtock, and not the Land; and ſo no Anceſtor could lay and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate ſuch a charge as tythe upon it, nor could he bind his ſucceſſor to it. If by my Anceſtor I am bound to pay tythes, <hi>ratione tenuree,</hi> or in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118978:17"/>conſideration of the Land which he leaves me, to what value muſt it be? I may yearly pay more then the Land he leaves me is worth: If I keep it in tillage, and if I paſture it, I need not pay the twentieth part; have not I herein (without fraud to my Anceſtors) power to pay much or little? how is this like a Rent-charge certain, which is by ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected? If tythes were paid by reaſon of the Land, ſurely there is moſt reaſon, that the tenth part of the graſſe renewing upon all paſture-grounds, ſhould be paid; for the Land ſtill brings that with it, and it's eaſily divideable by Rent, or let by moneth. If another hath as good right to the tenth part of the encreaſe as the owner hath to the nine, why can he not take it without the owners ſeuing it out, or recover it by Action of Debt or Treſpaſſe? But it is clear there is no title till it be ſet forth, and then if the owner carry it away, an Action of Treſpaſſe lies, becauſe he had ſet it out, and given it to another, and ſo altered his property, as one man doth by marking his Cattle for another man; and therefore it is that the Law which commands tythes doth not give power to any to take the tythe, becauſe he had no title, but enjoynes the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſet it forth, and ſo make it anothers by his own conſent.</p>
               <p>If any man claim tythes by my Anceſtors gift, may I not ask him, to whom, and for what my Anceſtors gave them? And it is plain, beyond denial, that all thoſe gifts of Lands or Tythes in <hi>Englard</hi> ſince <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> the Mouk planted the popiſh faith, and preached up the new pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tythes, were given to popiſh Prieſts for ſaying prayers for the ſouls of the givers, and their deceaſed Anceſtors, as old Conſecrations do witneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore in reaſon, if the conſideration and ſervice be ceaſed, ſo ought alſo the wages; for no man in law or equity ought to claim wages when he will not do the work for which it was given; and ſeeing thoſe popiſh Prieſts and Prayers are laid aſide, the gift (if any ſuch there were, and could be binding) ought to return to the Donor, and may not without his conſent be perverted to another uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tythe was never claimed in reſpect of any ownership in the Land, but</hi> ex debito,<note place="margin">SHEPHERD.</note> 
                  <hi>by the Law of God, for ſubſtraction whereof no remedy lay at the common-Law; and therefore if a Parſon let a Leaſe of his Glebe to another, with all the Appurtenances, yet he himſelf shall have tythe of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Terrae non ſunt decimbiles; and therefore neither Mynes nor Quaryes of Iron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">COOK.</note> 
                  <hi>Braſſe, Tin, Lead, Coles, Stones Tile, Brick, or Lime are tytheable, ner Houſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conſimilar is felony &amp; treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe between free-hold &amp; moveable goods.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Trees, nor Graſſe, or Corn, till they be ſevered from the Land, the real Estate which deſcends by inheritance from the Anceſtor, and made a diſtinct perſonal poſſeſsion.</hi> And therefore tythe is not paid of Land, nor by reaſon of the Land, nor is it a charge upon Land, like a Rent-charge, nor was it ever ſo claimed, till of late that the popiſh covers were not broad enough.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome object, and ſay, <hi>When I bought my Land, I bought not the tythe, nor paid any thing for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118978:17"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, That I and all men bought all our Land, and that without any charge of tythe upon it; and therefore in all Conveyances it's ſtill ſaid, <hi>All that, &amp;c.</hi> and never any covenant for, or exemption of a tenth part, either of land or encreaſe; and he that ſaith the ſeller or his Anceſtor charged it with tythes, as a Rent, I ſay, Where a Rent is charged, it's ſtill expreſſed; and finde any ſuch exception or covenant, and I will freely pay them as a juſt debt. And is it not ridiculous for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to talk of parchaſing his tythe? for with his labour, charge and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry he payes deere enough for his whole encreaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Another objects, <hi>That though I bought all my Land, yet I bought it cheaper (becauſe it was ſuppoſed that it ought to pay tythes) then I could have bought ſuch Land as was known to be tythe-free; and therefore having a cheaper bargain, I am bound in equity to pay tythes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, That I have already proved all Land is tythe-free, and the charge of tythe is upon the ſtock and perſonal Eſtate, and not upon the Land. And the ſtrength of this objection lies in comparing thoſe that pay tythes with thoſe that are free; they that buy lands tythe-free are eaſed of this oppreſſion, and are in no hazard; and though all others ought to be ſo, yet being a queſtion whether they can eaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the burthen, they buy under a hazard, and as ſubject to ſuch a charge; but if they can caſt off the yoke, they get but what is their own: And ſeeing we have denyed the Popes Authority and Supremacie, we may ſo ſoon as we can, wholly caſt off the burthens which he laid on us. And thus he that buyes Land in yeers of trouble and heavy taxes, may perhaps buy much cheaper then when none, or little is paid; ſhall he therefore alwaies be required to pay taxes when others are diſcharged? or ſhall he that bought cheap pennyworths on the borders between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> when thoſe parts were inſected with <hi>Moſſe</hi>-Troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, alwaies maintain, or pay tribute to thieves and robbers? We bought Land when the Popes yoke was upon our necks, and if we can caſt it from us, we may by as good reaſon be eaſed of our tythes, as they of their taxes. But if I bought cheaper, what is that to the State, or to a Prieſt? If in equity I be bound to pay any more, it is muſt juſt that he have it of whom I bought my Land, and not another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are others who plead a legal right by preſcription, and that they have a good right becauſe they have ſo long poſſeſsed them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the old device, firſt to preach that tythes were due, and then to limit them to the Pariſhes, and when fourty yeers was paſt, to claime that as a debt which before was paid as charity, or ar moſt, as a free-will-offering of the owner. And thus the Pope got firſt fruits, and tenths, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118978:18"/>
                  <hi>Peter</hi>-pence, and many great ſums out of this and other Nations, which long continued; and he might as well have pleaded his preſcription, as any of his branches now can do.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In temp. H.</hi> 3. the Pope had above 120000. l. <hi>per. an.</hi> out of this Nation, which was then more worth then the Kings revenue.</note> Is any ſo blind as not to ſee what poor ſhifts are now made to uphold ſo great an oppreſſion, which can find no better ground for its ſupport then this, <hi>that it hath been ſo long continued?</hi> But ſhall the continuance of an oppreſſion give right to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate the grievance? How many great and heavy preſſures in other things did long lye on this Nation, of cuſtoms and practices of former times, which daylie were, and ſtill have been aboliſhed, as light did more and more encreaſe? witneſs thoſe many Laws and Statutes made, and now in force, aboliſhing the uſages and cuſtoms of former ages; but yet this is a great miſtake; for by the Common-Law (and the old popiſh Eccleſiaſtick Law is out of doors) no man can preſcribe to have tythes, though many may preſcribe to be free from tythes, or part thereof; for he that claims tythes, (except Impropriators, to whom I ſhall ſpeake hereafter) muſt claim them as a Parſon, Vicar, or other called Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick Officer, and (as I have hinted before) he claims them not as ſuch a perſon, but as ſuch an Officer, and the preſcription (if any were) is to his Office. Now if no ſuch Office be in being, his claim is at an end: That there is now no ſuch Office, is plain; for when <hi>H.</hi> 8. renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Pope, he was declared by Act of Parliament (which was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to by all the Clergy in their Convention) to be the Head of the Church; and all Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, and all others in Eccleſiaſtical Orders, were no longer to hold of the Pope, but of the King; and not to claim their Benefices by title from the Pope, but of the King, by vertue of that Act of Parliament. And here the Succeſſion from the Pope was cut off, and diſcontinued, and the King by his new Authority, as Head of the Church, made Biſhops, and gave them power to make Parſons, Vicars, and others called Eccleſiaſtick Officers. Afterwards as the King renounced the Pope, ſo the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> laid aſide Kings, who had aſſumed the Title and Stile of Head of the Church, and alſo aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, and all their dependancies, root and branch; and here the whole Eccleſiaſtick ſtate was diſſolved, and the Body fell with the Head, and the Branches with the Root, both Parſons, Vicars and Curates, and all the whole progeny and off-ſpring, and ſo all their right, title, and claim to tythes was, and is at an end, as is more plainly and more fully ſet forth in a late printed paper, by <hi>Ier. Benſon,</hi> to which I refer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now I come to the laſt, thoſe that claim by purchaſe, and theſe are the Impropriators, and they ſay they have bought them of the State, and have paid great ſummes of money for them, and many of them have no other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118978:18"/>
To theſe I anſwer, That I have ſhewed before, that in the root all tythe is alike, whether it be now claimed by a Prieſt or an Impropriator, and both muſt fall together. And ſeeing thoſe that ſold them had no good title, neither can theirs be made good which is derived from them: But ſeeing it was the State that ſold them, and that the whole Nation had the benefit of their moneys, it is equal and juſt when they cannot have what is ſold, that their moneys be repaid; to which point I ſhall ſpeak more fully hereafter, in anſwer to an objection which I meet with in my way, needful to be reſolved.</p>
               <p>And thus I have briefly gone over the whole matter, and heard what every one can ſay, and have returned them anſwers, by which it doth plainly appear, That no man at this day can claim tythe of another, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by divine, or humane right; and that tythes are neither due by the expreſs Law of God, nor by the equity of that Law, nor by the Decrees of the Church, nor grants of Kings, nor Laws of Parliaments, nor gifts of the people, nor preſcription of the poſſeſſors, nor the purchaſe of Impropriators.</p>
               <p>It now onely remains that I anſwer ſome general objections, which I ſhall do in as much brevity at I can, and ſo leave the whole to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>The firſt is made by the State.</p>
               <p>The ſecond by Impropriators.</p>
               <p>And the third by Pariſh-Miniſters.</p>
               <p>And all theſe together object, and ſay, <hi>That though it should be granted that the right of tythes cannot be proved, yet if it be found that taking of them away will bring great loſſe to the Publique Revenue, much damage, if not ruine, to many particular perſons and families, and great hazard of bringing confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Nation by ſuch a great alteration after ſo long a ſettlement, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the very publike profeſsien of Religion by taking away Miniſters main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and conſequently Miniſtry it ſelf, it is not prudence for ſatisfying ſome, to bring ſo many and great inconveniences upon the Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe objections plead not for the right of tythes, but againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of them, to prevent inconvenience; and if the one be granted, that tythes are an innovated popiſh exaction and oppreſſion, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther due by law of God or man, ſuch conſiderations as theſe ought not to obſtruct the removal of ſo heavy a grievance and oppreſſion, but that which is juſt ought to be done, which is a general good to the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and almoſt every individual member, and then ſuch parts as are ſound grieved may be afterwards eaſed and relieved; and though all theſe ſhould in ſome meaſure ſuffer, it were but juſt, ſeeing their compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the oppreſſor hath brought ſuch a general yoke and barthen
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118978:19"/>upon the whole body, and now they are become the onely obſtructions of the general eaſement and publike freedom.</p>
               <p>And yet a few words I ſhall anſwer to every one, and firſt to the State which complains of a great loſſe by taking away firſt fruits and tenths, which are paid out of tythes.</p>
               <p>When the Pope had eſtabliſhed the payment of tythes, and ſet up a new Hierarchie after the pattern of the Jewiſh Prieſthood he tooke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on himſelf to be Succeſſor to the Jewiſh High-Prieſt,<note place="margin">Ierom in Ezek. ch. <hi>44.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi> &amp;c.</note> and claimed tenths from all his inferior prieſts, <hi>jure divino;</hi> and in proceſſe of time he got to himſelf by the like colour firſt fruits alſo; and though it was long ere he brought his work to paſs in <hi>England,</hi> yet at laſt it was effected: you may by theſe following inſtances know how much our <hi>English</hi> Nation ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King forbad</hi> H. P. <hi>the Popes Nuntio te collect firſt fruits.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Ed. <hi>3.</hi> Rol. Clauſ. M. <hi>4.</hi> Parl. <hi>1</hi> Ri. <hi>2.</hi> Nu. <hi>66.</hi> Rol Parl. <hi>4</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi> Nu. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Popes Collector was willed no longer to gather the firſt fruits, it being a very novelty, and no perſon was any longer to pay them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Commons Petition that proviſion may be made against the Popes Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors for levying of firſt fruits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King in Parliament anſwers, There shall be granted a prohibition in all ſuch caſes where the Popes Collectors shall attempt any ſuch Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon complaint made by the Commons in Parliament,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rol. Parl. <hi>6.</hi> R <hi>2.</hi> N. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the King willeth that Prohibitions be granted to the Popes Collectors for receiving of firſt fruits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First fruits by Arch-Bishops and Bishops to the Pope, were termed an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible miſchief,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> H. <hi>4.</hi> Rol. Parl. <hi>9</hi> H. <hi>4.</hi> N. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and damnable cuſtom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Popes Collector, were required from thenceforth not to levy any money within the Realm for firſt fruits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope thus claiming firſt fruits and tenths as annexed to his Chair, Succeſſor to the Jewiſh High-prieſt, and Head of the Church, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to collect them till <hi>H.</hi> 8. diſcontented with the Pope, though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was a papiſt, renounceth the Popes Supremacy, and aſſumes it to himſelf, and by Act of Parliament in 16. of his reign, got firſt fruits and tenths annexed to his Crown, as Head of the Church, and ſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf became worſe then the Pope, taking the wages, but not doing the Popes work; and that which before by Parliaments in height of popery was declared a damnable cuſtom, was now in the beginning of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation made a foundation-ſtone to ſupport the greatneſs of the new made Head.</p>
               <p>Afterwards <hi>Q. Mary</hi> not daring to aſſume the Head-ſhip of the Church, did relinquiſh, and by Act of Parliament wholly took away firſt fruits and tenths, ſhe doing no work to deſerve ſuch wages. And what a ſhame is this to our Nation, and our great profeſſions, after ſo long talk of reformation, now to plead for ſuch wages of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118978:19"/>firſt exacted by the Pope, and then by ſuch as aſſumed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſtile of Head of the Church, upon that very account had them annexed to the Crown? And ſhall we now who pretend to have caſt off the Pope, and left the Head-ſhip of the Church unto Chriſt, (worſe like then Queen <hi>Mary</hi>) uphold ſuch wicked oppreſſions, which are the ground of a great part of goods mens ſufferings for tythes this day? for the pretence of paying tenths is the ground of the many ſuits for tythes in the Exchequer, where otherwiſe by law they could not, nor ought to be recovered. And as to the Publique Revenue, I am informed they add not much thereunto, but all, or a great part of them are give in augmentations to Prieſts, who no doubt will receive them without ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though I know many of them not long ſince did complain againſt them as a popiſh oppreſſion. But take away tythes, and there are as many Glebe-Lands' will fall to the State as will fully make up that loſſe, which they may as well take away as their predeceſſors did the Revenues of Abbeys and Monaſteries; and when the people are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of tythes, they will be better able, and more willing to enlarge the Publique Treaſury if it be ſound wanting.</p>
               <p>But it's hoped our State rather looks at the freedom of the people, then the encreaſe of the Revenue, ſeeing ſo lately they took away the profits of the Court of <hi>Wards,</hi> which was a much better and greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and granted many great men ſuch freedom for nothing, as they could neither in right claim, nor in reaſon expect without a very great ſum, their Eſtates being given to them to hold by ſuch ſervices; and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will not deny the poorer ſort of people their own and deer-bought encreaſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>To Impropriators, and ſuch as have more lately bought Tythe-Rents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to theſe I ſay, Though it be a general Rule, <hi>Caveatemptor,</hi> yet ſeeing the ignorance of former dayes (but peeping out of popery) did take it for granted (both Buyer and Seller) that the title was good; and ſince the purchaſers did pay great ſums of money for them to the State, which went to the bearing and defraying the publike charge of the Nation, it is juſt that they have a moderate price for them, with which I believe moſt (if not all) of them would be well pleaſed and content; onely in the eſtimate of that rate they muſt conſider that they bought no more but what the Abbey, Monaſtery, or other diſſolved Houſe had; and theſe Houſes out of their appropriate tythes were to find a ſufficient Prieſt or Curate, Canonically inſtituted, which was to have allowance at the diſcretion of the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, and alſo a convenient portion of the tythe was to be ſet apart for the yeerly maintenance of the poor of the pariſh for ever, as is provided by divers
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118978:20"/>Acts of Parliament. And after the diſſolution and ſale of tythes, the like charge was and ought to be continued upon them, as at large is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a Treatiſe, called <hi>The poor Vicars Plea;</hi> and let but ſuch purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers look to their original Grants, &amp; they ſhall find that the yeerly value was but little, and the rate ſmall after which they paid for them; and in regard of the charges and hazards upon them, they were ſeldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eſteemed more worth then ten years purchaſe and that rate at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different yeerly value, may well beaccepted for them.</p>
               <p>This Anſwer will pleaſe the Impropriator well, who hath not been without his fears to loſe his tythes, and get little or nothing for them; and it cannot much diſpleaſe others becauſe it is equal and juſt, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he cannot have what is bought, he have his money returned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſſe.</p>
               <p>But the great difficulty ſeemeth the raiſing of ſo great a ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and who ſhall pay it; for firſt, There are many who plead, <hi>Our Lands are wholly tythe-free:</hi> Others ſay, <hi>We pay a Rate, or ſmall preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Rent, or have a</hi> modus decimandi, <hi>and our tythe is very ſmall, though our Lands be of good value.</hi> Others ſay, <hi>We have converted our Lands into Paſtures, and pay little tythe; and therefore it ſeems not equal that we should pay as much as thoſe whoſe Lands conſiſt of Tillage, whoſe tythes are often as much worth as the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, That the raiſing of this ſum is not to follow the Rate of tythe, nor hath it any relation to tythe; for if it had, many would as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcruple the payment of any thing towards it, as they do the payment of tythes; but the caſe muſt be thus conſidered: At the diſſolution, Tythes of Abbeys, Monaſteries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were taken into the hand of the State, they ſold them, and the money raiſed went to the defraying and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the great charge then upon the Nation, as it was of late in our dayes, when tythe-Rents were ſold, and at that day there were wars with <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and many great Exigences of State, as the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes for the ground of the diſſolution ſhews: And in the ſervice and uſe of theſe moneys, the whole Nation, and every man therein, had his ſhare; and ſo far as thoſe moneys went, the people were ſpared, as the Caſe was with us of late; and ſo he that had Land tythe-free, and he that paid onely a ſmall rate for tythes, and he that haſt paſtures and no tillage, all theſe ſhared in the ſum, yea and the very Impropriator himſelf, and not according to the proportion of tything, but according to the value of their Eſtates in Lands or Goods, by which they had been otherwiſe chargeable: And ſo the Impropriator depoſiting ſo much money upon a pledge, the one being required, the other muſt be return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by a general tax it muſt be raiſed, wherein every one muſt bear his proportion, the very Impropriator himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118978:20"/>
But then comes in he that bought the Lands of Abbeys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he ſaith, <hi>The Pope had made tythe-free, and that when he bought his Land, he alſo paid for the tythe, and ſo he must either be freed from paying to the Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priator, or muſt have his money returned as well as he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, Though there are many ſuch purchaſers, yet I believe to the freeing the Nation from this great and long-continued oppreſſion, they, or moſt part of them, would be content to contribute without any ſuch demand: But if any ſtand upon it, let him ſhew what he paid for his tythe, &amp; he ſhall have it, which was not a penny; for ſearch the Court of Augmentations, and it will be found that there was not in the value of Land the leaſt difference made between tythe-free, and that which paid tythes, as there was not of late in the ſale of Biſhops, and Dean and Chapters Lands, many of which alſo were as much tythe-free; and ſo if they bought Land tythe-free as cheap as if they had paid tythes, they have had profit enough, and may now well afford to pay with their neighbors.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>To Parish-Miniſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And with theſe I deſire a little to expoſtulate the matter, firſt, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the end of their work; and ſecondly, as to the way of their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. Their work, as they pretend, is to preach the Goſpel, and to propagate Religion: Now I would ask them, why they ſuffer (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo many Villages, Countrey-Towns, and Pariſhes, but) even great and populous Cities and Market-Towns, and whole corners of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys to lye deſtitute, who never could get any other Miniſter then a poor Vicar, or Reading Curate; they will preſently anſwer me, There is no maintenance, without that they cannot live. If I ask them further, Why there is no maintenance; they will tell me, It is either a City or Market-Town to which there belongs no Land, and ſo no tythes, or it is an Impropriation, and payes onely a ſmall ſtipend, or the Lands are tythe-free, or claim cuſtoms and preſcriptions, and onely pay ſmall rates for tythes, or otherwiſe the people have converted their arable Lands into paſtures, and their tythe is of ſmall value, and will not afford a maintenance. I would yet ask them again, Is not a third part of the Nation in this condition? and muſt they never have an able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter? have they no ſhare in your Goſpel becauſe they have no main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance? Are none of your called to ſuch places? Or hath Chriſt no Seed of Election amongſt them? If this be not your Doctrine, yet your practice preacheth it: And if you were really for ſpreading your Goſpel, and enlarging profeſſion, you would forthwith throw away tythes; for ſo long as they continue, there can never be any poſſibility of raiſing maintenance in ſuch places.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118978:21"/>
And ſecondly, As to their Maintenance, is there any indifferency, equality, proportion, or juſtice in their preſent way of tything? One man pleads he is to pay nothing to a Miniſter, becauſe the Pope hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a diſpenſation, and made his Land tythe-free. Another man ſaith, he hath a preſcription to pay but a penny (it may be) for the value of a ſhilling. Another ſaith, he hath converted his Lands into paſtures, and hath by his Artifice ſo ordered it, that little is due for tythes. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, he dwells in a City or Market-Town, and hath no Land, though it's like he gains more by trade then ten poor countrey-men that pay tythes, do by their Lands. Another ſaith, he payes tythe to an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriator, and he cannot afford to pay both him and a Miniſter. Is this your equal way of maintenance ſo long upheld and pleaded for? And have you not a more righteous Rule? The rich generally payes lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and the poor Husbandman bears the burthen, even he that ſupplies the Nation, with the ſtaffe of Bread, who is notwithſtanding, at more charge in his Husbandry then any other; and out of the tythe of ſuch countrey-pariſhes of Tillage, generally great ſums are paid for Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to Cities and Market-Towns, when the Inhabitants that have far greater gains by trading go free. For ſhame at length follow the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of your neighboring reformed Churches, and throw away tythes as an old relique of Popery, and no longer halt between two, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take your ſelves to a more Goſpel-like way of maintenance; for light now breaks forth, and pretences will no longer cover.</p>
               <p>It's like you wil anſwer, <hi>We confeſſe the preſent way of maintenance by tythes is very unequal, unleſs the whole Nation could be brought to quit all their cuſtomes and preſcriptions, and pay tythe in kind; and alſo all Merchants and Tradeſmen would pay the tenth part of their gains, as was by the Pope en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned; but that will never be done, and therefore its better to hold ſome, then loſe all; for we know not what better way would be provided: But thew us how we may have a comfortable and certain maintenance, and more like the Goſpel, and we shall moſt willingly quit the one, and embrace the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That there is a way which as it would eſtabliſh the Nation upon a ſure foundation of true freedom (as to the conſcience) giving content to all ſeparated Congregations, Societies and perſons, ſo would it upon the ſame Baſis of Liberty hold forth full ſatisfaction to all people of the Nation, both as to Miniſtry and Maintenance, and would be as acceptable to every one as the taking away tythes. But I have ſaid enough at once, and when this is a little digeſted, the other will be more fit to be propoſed.</p>
               <p>Onely to ſuch as fear confuſion, or trouble, or loſſe to the Nation by taking away tythes, I would ſay a few words: Do but look into almoſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118978:21"/>every Country Town, and there ſhall you find debate, ſtrife, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, either between man and man, or between Pariſhes and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, either about tythe it ſelf, the quantity, or the ſetting it out; look into Courts, and there you ſhall find Suit upon Suit; and at Aſſizes, and before Juſtices of Peace, multitudes of Tryals and Judgements about them: Look into Priſons, and there you ſhall find not a few reſtrained, and lying under great oppreſſions becauſe they cannot pay them: And theſe ſuits and troubles are daylie encreaſing, and the number of thoſe that will not pay them, and theſe are no ſmall confuſions in our State; for it is evident, there are more ſuits, and ſtrife, and difference about tythes, then any one thing whatſoever in the Nation; and how ſoon might all theſe be ended, and every one ſatisfied, by taking away tythes? And then do but look upon the many Moores, Commons, and Waſtes in the Nation, amounting to a full third part of the whole, as hath been computed, to the many great Paſtures and Meadows decayed for want of tillage, to the many countreys which are turned into Paſtures and Meadows becauſe of the great charge of tillage, husbandry, and the unreaſonable payment of a clear tenth part, which in moſt places is half the profit, and it will be found, nothing doth ſo much hinder the improvement of the Nation, which would eaſe the publike burthens, and would ſoon be of more advantage then firſt fruits and tenths. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much hinders Tillage, which often puts the Nation upon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of ruine, and forceth us to ſeek bread out of other Countreys at immoderate rates, when as this Nation is generally ſo fit for Corn, that it might be as a rich Granary, not onely for our own ſupply, but reliefe of our Neighbors when they want. I might ſay a great deal more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſubject, but much to this purpoſe hath been ſaid by others, and therefore I ſhall conclude.</p>
               <p>And let no man henceforth think it ſtrange that any ſhould refuſe to pay tythes, but rather wonder that any will do it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:118978:22"/>
            <p>THis is not written for them that know the truth, but for them which know not the truth, that they might be informed from the Light which ſees the truth through the Reaſon, to the ſame in the world, that the truth they may ſee and underſtand in their own language.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118978:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
